Guide to the Actors' Equity Association Photographs PHOTOS.049
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Actors' Equity Association Photographs
1900-1974
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Actors' Equity Association
PHOTOS.049
1 box
Actors' Equity Association (AEA, "Equity"), the premiere theatrical performers' labor union in the United States, was founded in New York City in 1913, as the first of the American actors' unions. Its jurisdiction covers both actors and stage managers in the professional theater. The collection contains approximately 110 black and white photographs (and one negative), ranging in size from 3x5 to 8x10 inches. Although it encompasses a miscellany that includes images of AEA offices, AEA meetings, actors and actresses, and theaters, very little of Equity's early history is represented.
51 folders; ca. 110 items (3x5; 5x7; 8x10; b&w prints; 8x10 b&w negative)
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Actors' Equity Association in 1982 and separated from the Actors' Equity Association Records (WAG 011). The accession number associated with this gift is 1982.003.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically by topic within series, except for Series III (People) and IV (Theaters), which are arranged alphabetically by name.
This collection is organized into five series:
Missing Title
I. Actors' Equity Association
II. Events
III. People
IV. Theaters
V. Miscellaneous.
Historical Note
Actors' Equity Association (AEA, Equity), the premiere theatrical performers' labor union in the United States, was founded in New York City in 1913 as the first of the American actors' unions. In July 1919, the American Federation of Labor (later to be the AFL-CIO) granted a charter to Equity as an autonomous branch of the newly-formed Associated Actors and Artists of America. One month later, Equity called the first actors' strike in the history of the American theater.
Today Equity's jurisdiction covers both actors and stage managers in the professional theater. It is governed by a council of delegates elected by its membership. Its headquarters are in New York City; it also maintains branches in Chicago, Los Angeles, and Orlando, Florida.
Sources:
For further historical information on the Actors' Equity Association and to review the scope and contents of its records, see Guide to Records of the Actors' Equity Association(Wagner #11). See also About Equity -- A Handbook(New York: Actors' Equity Association), and the Actors' Equity Association website: http://www.actorsequity.org/home.html.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Actors' Equity Association Records (Wagner 11)
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains approximately 110 black and white photographs (and one negative), ranging in size from 3x5 to 8x10 inches; it encompasses a miscellany that includes images of Actors' Equity Association (AEA) offices, AEA meetings, actors and actresses, and theaters. Other than a 1919 production photograph of Brandon Tynan performing in "Equity" (a play created as a benefit during the organization's first strike), very little early AEA history is represented. Most of the images of theaters were evidently shot to document bad working conditions, so many of them show stage-door entrances littered with garbage and interiors with crumbling walls and defective plumbing, rather than glamorous facades. Notable images include a picket line by the Oriental Actors Guild in 1968, and Equity members, circa the early 1960s, gathered at the AEA New York City office's "Equity Lounge" to look for work and avail themselves of other member services. Only a few of the individual actors and actresses identified (in portraits or in production photographs) are prominent. They include: Ethel Barrymore; Ralph Bellamy; Jeanette Conner; John Cornell; William H. Crane; Butho Davenport; Paul Dullzell; Philip Loeb; Alan Howland; Harrison Hoy; Colin Keith; George Pierce; Elaine Klaw Roesen; Blythe Sherwood; Marguerite Sylva; and Cyril Vane.
Actresses -- United States -- Portraits; Actors |x Labor unions |z United States |v Portraits.; Actors |z United States |v Portraits.; Negatives (photographic); Black-and-white photographs.; Portraits.; Davenport, Butho -- Portraits.; Crane, William H., 1845-1928 -- Pictorial works.; Cornell, John -- Pictorial works. -- Portraits.; Conner, Jeanette -- Pictorial works -- Portraits.; Sylva, Marguerite, 1875-1957; Roesen, Elaine Claw -- Portraits; Pierce, George -- Portraits.; Keith, Colin -- Portraits.; Howland, Alan -- Portraits.; Hoy, Harrison -- Portraits.; Loeb, Philip, 1894-1955 -- Portraits.; Dullzell, Paul -- Portraits.; Oriental Actors of America; Vane, Cyril -- Portraits.; Tynan, Brandon, 1875-1967 -- Portraits.; Barrymore, Ethel, 1879-1959 -- Pictorial works.; Actors' Equity Association -- Pictorial works.
- Series I: Actors' Equity Association.
  - AEA (unidentified) Groundbreaking - some ID of individuals, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - AEA Meeting, Contact Sheet, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - AEA Meeting, Western Regional Membership, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Los Angeles Office, AEA, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Los Angeles Office, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - New York Office, AEA, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - New York Office, AEA, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - New York Office Photos, 226 W. 47th St., NY, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - New York Office, 165 W. 46th St., NY, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - New York Office, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - New York Office, Credit Union Annual Meeting, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - New York Office, Meeting, Mar 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - New York Office, Players Club Dinner, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - New York Office, Labor News Conference, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - New York Office, Picket Line Supporting Soviet Dissidents, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series II: Events.
  - Paul Robeson Awards Ceremony, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Lillian Russell Memorial Service, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series III: People.
  - Barrymore, Ethel, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bellamy, Ralph, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Booth, Edwin (Bust), undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Chorines Waiting to Audition, [1920-1929] (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Conner, Jeanette; Hoy, Harrison, [1920-1929] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cooke, George Frederick (Tomb of), undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Cornell, John, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Crane, William H, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Davenport, Butho, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Dullzell, Paul; Pierce, George "The Trainer", undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Loeb, Philip (Negatives), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Oriental Actors of America, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Roesen, Elaine Klaw 1968 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Sherwood, Blythe, [1910-1920] (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Sylva, Mme. Marguerite, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Tynan, Brandon (in "Equity"), 1919 (Box Tamiment Shared OS006, Folder 1, Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Vane, Cyril (Marcellus); Keith, Colin (Hamlet); Howland, Alan (Horatio), undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Series IV: Theaters.
  - Academy of Music (New York City), 1926 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Baird Marionette Theater (Jaipur, India), undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Baker Theater (Fort Leonard Wood, Missouri), undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Castle Square Garden, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Grand Ole Opry House [Ryman Auditorium], backstage (Nashville, Tennessee), 1964 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - La Salle Theater, Stage Entrance (New York City), 1923 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Nixon Theater, Backstage (Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Olympic Theater, Stage Entrance (New York City), 1923 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Paramount Theater, Backstage (Portland, Oregon), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Portable Theater, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - State Fair Music Hall (Dallas, Texas), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Theaters, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Walnut Street Theater (Philadelphia, PA), 1926 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Series V: Miscellaneous.
  - "The Little Racketeer," Billboard, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Shakespearean Portraits, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Stage Society Placard, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Veterans Music Program - The Veterans Bedside Network (not AEA) - separate organization, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Unidentified Old Photos, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)